so let's look at a better implementation
of sequential consistency in which a
core can reorder loads but this can lead
to violations of sequential consistency
so it has to also detect when sequential
consistency may be violated and fixed
things
this is of course easy to say but how do
we really do that so let's look at a
program where there is a load to a and
then sometime later but not too much
later a load from B so we need to make
this execute in order if doing otherwise
will violate sequential consistency but
we want to really execute them out of
order if there is no potential for
sequential consistency violation
so let's look at what happens in the
reorder buffer of a processor that tries
to execute this the reorder buffer keeps
instructions in program order so the
first load will be
known to come ahead of the second load
now if we actually do this axis first
and this second then there is no
potential for violating sequential
consistency because we are actually
doing whatever the simple implementation
would do anyway so the sequential
consistency evaluation can occur when we
first
do load B
in our real execution order
and later for example because the
computation for address of a has been
delayed we do load of a now the
important thing to note is that this is
not necessarily a violation of
sequential consistency if nobody writes
either b or a during this time then the
B here and the a here will be the same
as if we reorder them back to their
original program order so we are getting
the same value of B no matter where we
load it
if nobody writes anything
in fact
for this to actually be a violation of
sequential consistency like we can
actually get a different value for B
than we could in sequential consistency
what has to happen is that there is at
least one store to be
between the time we actually read B
and the time when we should have read B
according to sequential consistency why
well because if we don't have the store
here
then the value we write here is the same
as the value that we would have read
here where it would be okay to read B so
now we can see how we can detect
violations of sequential consistency
when we read something ahead of program
order we need to start monitoring the
coherence traffic produced by other
processors so if we see such a store
then this load and anything that it fed
the data to must be replayed note that
this load is replayable because in the
Rob it's here
we are assuming that this load still
hasn't happened which means that the
commit pointer for the Rob is somewhere
here or maybe at the load here but
definitely the load from B has not been
committed so we are capable of replaying
it in the worst case
we can just cancel this load and
anything that follows and just refetch
those instructions so we know how to
undo the damage here but in order to
detect the violation now we have to
basically anything that we load out of
order we need to monitor coherence
traffic until that load becomes in order